<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<learning>
  <metadata>
    <title>Prevent .env File Loading in Staging/Production</title>
    <category>security</category>
    <subcategory>environment-configuration</subcategory>
    <severity>critical</severity>
    <date>2025-08-30</date>
    <related_files>
      <file>netra_backend/app/core/isolated_environment.py</file>
      <file>tests/unit/test_env_file_staging_protection.py</file>
    </related_files>
  </metadata>

  <problem>
    <description>
      The IsolatedEnvironment class was automatically loading .env files in ALL environments,
      including staging and production. This creates a security risk where development secrets
      could accidentally be deployed or override production secrets from the deployment system.
    </description>
    <root_cause>
      The _auto_load_env_file() method in IsolatedEnvironment.__init__ was loading .env files
      without checking the current environment. This happens at singleton initialization,
      affecting all subsequent environment variable access.
    </root_cause>
    <impact>
      - Development secrets could leak to production
      - Production secrets could be overridden by .env files
      - Configuration inconsistencies between expected and actual values
      - Security vulnerabilities from exposed development credentials
    </impact>
  </problem>

  <solution>
    <approach>
      Modified _auto_load_env_file() to check the ENVIRONMENT variable and skip loading
      .env files when running in staging or production environments.
    </approach>
    <implementation>
      <code_change file="netra_backend/app/core/isolated_environment.py">
        Added environment check at the beginning of _auto_load_env_file():
        ```python
        # Check current environment - never load .env in staging/production
        environment = os.environ.get('ENVIRONMENT', '').lower()
        if environment in ['staging', 'production']:
            logger.debug(f"Skipping .env file loading in {environment} environment")
            return
        ```
      </code_change>
    </implementation>
    <validation>
      Created comprehensive test suite (test_env_file_staging_protection.py) that verifies:
      - .env files are NOT loaded in staging environment
      - .env files are NOT loaded in production environment  
      - .env files ARE loaded in development environment
      - .env files do not override existing environment variables
    </validation>
  </solution>

  <best_practices>
    <practice>
      NEVER load .env files in staging or production environments.
      These environments should only use environment variables set by the deployment system.
    </practice>
    <practice>
      Always check the environment before loading configuration files.
      Development conveniences should not affect production security.
    </practice>
    <practice>
      When loading .env files in development, never override existing environment variables.
      This ensures deployment system values take precedence.
    </practice>
  </best_practices>

  <prevention>
    <recommendation>
      Add environment checks to ALL configuration loading code.
      Any convenience features for development should be explicitly disabled in production.
    </recommendation>
    <recommendation>
      Consider using separate configuration classes for different environments
      rather than conditional logic within a single class.
    </recommendation>
    <recommendation>
      Add CI/CD checks that verify .env files are not present in production deployments.
    </recommendation>
  </prevention>

  <testing_requirements>
    <test>Verify .env files are ignored in staging/production</test>
    <test>Verify .env files are loaded in development</test>
    <test>Verify existing environment variables are not overridden</test>
    <test>Test with various ENVIRONMENT values (staging, production, development, test, empty)</test>
  </testing_requirements>
</learning>