<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<learning>
    <metadata>
        <title>MRO Conflict Resolution - Diamond Inheritance Pattern Fix</title>
        <date>2025-01-09</date>
        <impact>critical</impact>
        <business_value>unblocks_integration_tests_protecting_120k_mrr</business_value>
        <category>inheritance_patterns</category>
        <claude_md_section>3.6</claude_md_section>
    </metadata>

    <problem>
        <description>
            TestLoadBalancerHeaderPropagation(BaseIntegrationTest, WebSocketIntegrationTest) 
            created diamond inheritance pattern causing MRO conflict blocking ALL integration tests.
        </description>
        <error_message>
            TypeError: Cannot create a consistent method resolution order (MRO) 
            for bases BaseIntegrationTest, WebSocketIntegrationTest
        </error_message>
        <root_cause>
            Diamond Problem: WebSocketIntegrationTest already inherits from BaseIntegrationTest,
            so inheriting from both creates circular MRO dependency.
        </root_cause>
    </problem>

    <solution>
        <approach>Single Inheritance Pattern</approach>
        <implementation>
            Changed: class TestLoadBalancerHeaderPropagation(BaseIntegrationTest, WebSocketIntegrationTest)
            To: class TestLoadBalancerHeaderPropagation(WebSocketIntegrationTest)
        </implementation>
        <rationale>
            WebSocketIntegrationTest already inherits all BaseIntegrationTest functionality,
            so single inheritance provides complete access without conflicts.
        </rationale>
    </solution>

    <validation>
        <mro_hierarchy>
            TestLoadBalancerHeaderPropagation → WebSocketIntegrationTest → 
            BaseIntegrationTest → ABC → object
        </mro_hierarchy>
        <functionality_preserved>
            - setup_method ✓
            - async_setup ✓ 
            - async_teardown ✓
            - assert_business_value_delivered ✓
            - verify_websocket_event_delivery ✓
            - All test methods accessible ✓
        </functionality_preserved>
        <business_impact>
            Integration tests can now execute to validate authentication header propagation
            that protects $120K+ MRR authentication infrastructure.
        </business_impact>
    </validation>

    <patterns>
        <diamond_inheritance>
            <problem>
                Multiple inheritance from parent and child classes creates MRO conflicts
            </problem>
            <solution>
                Always inherit from the most derived class only - it provides full functionality
            </solution>
            <detection>
                RuntimeError on class creation with "Cannot create consistent MRO" message
            </detection>
        </diamond_inheritance>
        
        <prevention>
            <mro_analysis>
                Always analyze inheritance chains before creating multiple inheritance patterns
            </mro_analysis>
            <visualization>
                Draw inheritance diagrams to identify diamond patterns before implementation
            </visualization>
            <prefer_single>
                Prefer single inheritance or composition over complex multiple inheritance
            </prefer_single>
        </prevention>
    </patterns>

    <claude_md_compliance>
        <section_3_6>
            <mro_report>Comprehensive MRO analysis completed per Section 3.6 requirements</mro_report>
            <five_whys>Five Whys analysis identified root cause as diamond inheritance pattern</five_whys>
            <method_shadowing>No method shadowing conflicts detected</method_shadowing>
            <ssot_solution>Single inheritance maintains SSOT principle while eliminating conflicts</ssot_solution>
        </section_3_6>
    </claude_md_compliance>

    <lessons_learned>
        <inheritance_design>
            1. Always check inheritance chains before multiple inheritance
            2. Diamond patterns are common with test base classes
            3. Single inheritance from most derived class usually sufficient
            4. MRO errors block entire test execution - high business impact
        </inheritance_design>
        
        <test_architecture>
            1. Test base classes should document their inheritance clearly
            2. Prefer composition over inheritance for complex test patterns
            3. Validate test class creation in CI to catch MRO issues early
            4. Integration tests are critical for business value validation
        </test_architecture>

        <ssot_principles>
            1. One inheritance path provides complete functionality
            2. Multiple paths to same functionality violate SSOT
            3. Single inheritance preserves functionality while eliminating conflicts
            4. Business value must be preserved during refactoring
        </ssot_principles>
    </lessons_learned>

    <files_affected>
        <file>netra_backend/tests/integration/test_load_balancer_header_propagation.py</file>
        <change>Modified inheritance declaration to single inheritance</change>
        <impact>Unblocked ALL integration tests execution</impact>
    </files_affected>

    <future_prevention>
        <automated_checks>
            Add MRO validation to test discovery phase
        </automated_checks>
        <documentation>
            Document inheritance patterns in test base classes
        </documentation>
        <code_review>
            Include inheritance pattern review in checklist
        </code_review>
    </future_prevention>
</learning>