<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<specification>
    <title>Model Context Protocol (MCP) Integration</title>
    <version>1.0</version>
    <date>2025-08-26</date>
    <status>active</status>
    
    <purpose>
        <overview>
            MCP (Model Context Protocol) is a standard protocol developed by Anthropic for enabling
            seamless communication between AI models and external tools/services. FastMCP is a Python
            framework that implements this protocol, providing a high-performance, type-safe way to
            expose tools and context to AI models.
        </overview>
        <business_value>
            - Enables AI agents to interact with external systems through standardized tool interfaces
            - Provides context sharing capabilities for improved agent understanding
            - Facilitates multi-agent collaboration through shared protocols
            - Ensures type safety and validation for tool inputs/outputs
        </business_value>
    </purpose>
    
    <dependency_requirement>
        <package>fastmcp</package>
        <version>2.11.3</version>
        <location>requirements.txt</location>
        <reason>
            Required for MCP service implementation in netra_backend/app/services/mcp_service.py.
            This service enables:
            1. Tool registration and execution for AI agents
            2. Context server capabilities for sharing system state
            3. Standardized communication protocol with Claude and other AI models
            4. Type-safe tool parameter validation
        </reason>
    </dependency_requirement>
    
    <implementation_details>
        <core_components>
            <component name="MCPService">
                <path>netra_backend/app/services/mcp_service.py</path>
                <description>
                    Main service class that manages MCP server instances, tool registration,
                    and execution context. Provides the foundation for exposing Netra's
                    capabilities as tools to AI models.
                </description>
            </component>
            
            <component name="MCPHandlers">
                <path>netra_backend/app/routes/mcp/handlers.py</path>
                <description>
                    HTTP route handlers for MCP endpoints, enabling external clients to
                    discover and execute tools through the MCP protocol.
                </description>
            </component>
            
            <component name="MCPToolExecution">
                <path>netra_backend/app/services/mcp_service.py</path>
                <description>
                    Handles the actual execution of tools, including parameter validation,
                    error handling, and response formatting according to MCP standards.
                </description>
            </component>
        </core_components>
        
        <tool_categories>
            <category name="Data Operations">
                <description>Tools for querying and manipulating data in PostgreSQL and ClickHouse</description>
            </category>
            <category name="Agent Management">
                <description>Tools for creating, configuring, and managing AI agents</description>
            </category>
            <category name="System Administration">
                <description>Tools for monitoring, debugging, and maintaining the Netra platform</description>
            </category>
            <category name="Integration">
                <description>Tools for connecting with external services and APIs</description>
            </category>
        </tool_categories>
    </implementation_details>
    
    <protocol_features>
        <feature name="Tool Discovery">
            <description>
                Clients can discover available tools and their schemas through the
                /mcp/tools endpoint, enabling dynamic tool selection by AI models.
            </description>
        </feature>
        
        <feature name="Type Safety">
            <description>
                All tool parameters and return values are strongly typed using Pydantic
                models, ensuring data integrity and reducing runtime errors.
            </description>
        </feature>
        
        <feature name="Context Sharing">
            <description>
                MCP servers can share context about the current system state, user session,
                and environment, allowing AI models to make more informed decisions.
            </description>
        </feature>
        
        <feature name="Error Handling">
            <description>
                Standardized error responses allow AI models to gracefully handle tool
                execution failures and provide meaningful feedback to users.
            </description>
        </feature>
    </protocol_features>
    
    <integration_points>
        <integration name="Claude Desktop">
            <description>
                FastMCP servers can be directly integrated with Claude Desktop app,
                allowing Claude to use Netra's tools natively.
            </description>
        </integration>
        
        <integration name="LangChain">
            <description>
                MCP tools can be exposed as LangChain tools, enabling integration
                with the broader LangChain ecosystem.
            </description>
        </integration>
        
        <integration name="Custom Clients">
            <description>
                Any client that implements the MCP protocol can discover and use
                Netra's tools through the standardized HTTP/WebSocket interface.
            </description>
        </integration>
    </integration_points>
    
    <security_considerations>
        <consideration name="Authentication">
            <description>
                MCP endpoints require proper authentication through Netra's auth service
                to prevent unauthorized tool execution.
            </description>
        </consideration>
        
        <consideration name="Authorization">
            <description>
                Tool access is controlled through role-based permissions, ensuring users
                can only execute tools they're authorized to use.
            </description>
        </consideration>
        
        <consideration name="Input Validation">
            <description>
                All tool inputs are validated against their schemas before execution,
                preventing injection attacks and malformed requests.
            </description>
        </consideration>
    </security_considerations>
    
    <future_enhancements>
        <enhancement name="Tool Versioning">
            <description>Support for multiple versions of tools with backward compatibility</description>
        </enhancement>
        
        <enhancement name="Tool Composition">
            <description>Ability to compose complex tools from simpler building blocks</description>
        </enhancement>
        
        <enhancement name="Performance Metrics">
            <description>Built-in metrics for tool execution time, success rates, and usage patterns</description>
        </enhancement>
    </future_enhancements>
</specification>