<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<mega_class_exceptions>
  <metadata>
    <created>2025-08-31</created>
    <updated>2025-09-08</updated>
    <purpose>Define exceptions for central SSOT classes that can exceed standard module size limits</purpose>
    <rationale>Some central classes serve as Single Source of Truth and must contain comprehensive functionality that cannot be meaningfully split without violating SSOT principles</rationale>
    <related_documentation>
      <reference>reports/architecture/OVER_ENGINEERING_AUDIT_20250908.md</reference>
      <reference>reports/architecture/MANAGER_RENAMING_PLAN_20250908.md</reference>
      <reference>SPEC/naming_conventions_business_focused.xml</reference>
    </related_documentation>
  </metadata>

  <limits>
    <standard_module_limit>750</standard_module_limit>
    <mega_class_limit>2000</mega_class_limit>
    <standard_function_limit>25</standard_function_limit>
    <mega_class_function_limit>50</mega_class_function_limit>
  </limits>

  <exception_criteria>
    <criterion>Must be a Single Source of Truth (SSOT) for its domain</criterion>
    <criterion>Must serve as a central integration point for multiple services</criterion>
    <criterion>Splitting would violate SSOT principles or create circular dependencies</criterion>
    <criterion>Must be explicitly documented and justified in this file</criterion>
    <criterion>Must have comprehensive test coverage (>90%)</criterion>
    <criterion>Functions within mega classes can be up to 50 lines if they coordinate multiple operations</criterion>
  </exception_criteria>

  <approved_exceptions>
    <exception>
      <path>/netra_backend/app/db/database_manager.py</path>
      <current_size>1825</current_size>
      <max_allowed>2000</max_allowed>
      <justification>
        Central SSOT for all database operations across the platform.
        Contains unified interfaces for PostgreSQL, ClickHouse, and Redis.
        Splitting would require duplicate connection management and transaction handling.
      </justification>
      <requirements>
        <requirement>Must maintain single connection pool per database type</requirement>
        <requirement>Must provide unified transaction management</requirement>
        <requirement>Must centralize all database configuration</requirement>
      </requirements>
    </exception>

    <exception>
      <path>/netra_backend/app/websocket_core/manager.py</path>
      <current_size>1718</current_size>
      <max_allowed>2000</max_allowed>
      <justification>
        Central WebSocket manager handling all real-time communications.
        Critical for chat functionality (90% of platform value).
        Contains WebSocket lifecycle, event routing, and agent integration.
        Splitting would break real-time event flow and create race conditions.
      </justification>
      <requirements>
        <requirement>Must maintain single WebSocket connection per client</requirement>
        <requirement>Must handle all agent event types in one place</requirement>
        <requirement>Must provide centralized connection state management</requirement>
      </requirements>
    </exception>

    <exception>
      <path>/unified_test_runner.py</path>
      <current_size>1728</current_size>
      <max_allowed>2000</max_allowed>
      <justification>
        Central test orchestration for entire platform.
        Must coordinate unit, integration, E2E, and mission-critical tests.
        Contains all test discovery, execution, and reporting logic.
        Splitting would fragment test configuration and reporting.
      </justification>
      <requirements>
        <requirement>Must provide single entry point for all test types</requirement>
        <requirement>Must maintain unified test configuration</requirement>
        <requirement>Must generate consolidated test reports</requirement>
      </requirements>
    </exception>

    <exception>
      <path>/scripts/deploy_to_gcp.py</path>
      <current_size>1437</current_size>
      <max_allowed>2000</max_allowed>
      <justification>
        Central deployment orchestrator for GCP.
        Contains all build, push, and deployment logic for multiple services.
        Must coordinate frontend, backend, auth service deployments.
        Splitting would risk deployment inconsistencies.
      </justification>
      <requirements>
        <requirement>Must maintain atomic deployment transactions</requirement>
        <requirement>Must provide rollback capability for all services</requirement>
        <requirement>Must centralize all GCP configuration</requirement>
      </requirements>
    </exception>

    <exception>
      <path>/netra_backend/app/core/managers/unified_lifecycle_manager.py</path>
      <current_size>1950</current_size>
      <max_allowed>2000</max_allowed>
      <justification>
        SSOT for all lifecycle operations consolidating 100+ legacy managers.
        Central integration point for startup, shutdown, health monitoring.
        Critical for zero-downtime deployments and chat service reliability.
        Contains factory pattern for multi-user isolation and WebSocket coordination.
        Splitting would break lifecycle coordination and create race conditions.
      </justification>
      <requirements>
        <requirement>Must handle all component lifecycle phases atomically</requirement>
        <requirement>Must provide user-isolated lifecycle management</requirement>
        <requirement>Must coordinate with WebSocket events for real-time notifications</requirement>
        <requirement>Must maintain comprehensive health monitoring</requirement>
      </requirements>
    </exception>

    <exception>
      <path>/netra_backend/app/core/managers/unified_configuration_manager.py</path>
      <current_size>1890</current_size>
      <max_allowed>2000</max_allowed>
      <justification>
        SSOT for all configuration management consolidating 50+ config managers.
        Central configuration store with multi-source precedence and validation.
        Critical for eliminating configuration drift across environments.
        Contains service-specific configuration creation and IsolatedEnvironment integration.
        Splitting would fragment configuration consistency and validation.
      </justification>
      <requirements>
        <requirement>Must use IsolatedEnvironment for all environment variable access</requirement>
        <requirement>Must validate against MISSION_CRITICAL_NAMED_VALUES_INDEX</requirement>
        <requirement>Must provide service-specific configuration methods</requirement>
        <requirement>Must support multi-user configuration isolation</requirement>
      </requirements>
    </exception>

    <exception>
      <path>/netra_backend/app/core/managers/unified_state_manager.py</path>
      <current_size>1820</current_size>
      <max_allowed>2000</max_allowed>
      <justification>
        SSOT for all state management consolidating 50+ state managers.
        Central state store with scoped isolation and TTL-based expiration.
        Critical for agent state consistency and WebSocket synchronization.
        Contains multi-user state isolation and comprehensive querying capabilities.
        Splitting would break state consistency and create synchronization issues.
      </justification>
      <requirements>
        <requirement>Must provide thread-safe state operations with fine-grained locking</requirement>
        <requirement>Must support scoped state isolation (user, session, thread, agent)</requirement>
        <requirement>Must integrate with WebSocket manager for real-time state sync</requirement>
        <requirement>Must provide comprehensive state querying and filtering</requirement>
      </requirements>
    </exception>
  </approved_exceptions>

  <rejected_candidates>
    <candidate>
      <path>/netra_backend/app/db/clickhouse.py</path>
      <current_size>943</current_size>
      <rejection_reason>
        Not truly central - specific to ClickHouse operations only.
        Can be refactored to use database_manager.py as SSOT.
        Size is manageable with minor refactoring.
      </rejection_reason>
    </candidate>

    <candidate>
      <path>/frontend/auth/context.tsx</path>
      <current_size>Unknown</current_size>
      <rejection_reason>
        Frontend auth context should be lightweight.
        Complex logic should be in backend auth service.
        fetchAuthConfig function (166 lines) must be refactored.
      </rejection_reason>
    </candidate>
  </rejected_candidates>

  <refactoring_guidelines>
    <guideline>
      Classes approaching 2000 lines must be reviewed quarterly for potential refactoring.
    </guideline>
    <guideline>
      New additions to mega classes must be justified in pull requests.
    </guideline>
    <guideline>
      Functions within mega classes should still aim for <25 lines where possible.
    </guideline>
    <guideline>
      Mega classes must maintain internal organization with clear sections and documentation.
    </guideline>
    <guideline>
      Consider using composition or delegation patterns before expanding mega classes.
    </guideline>
  </refactoring_guidelines>

  <compliance_notes>
    <note>
      Files exceeding 2000 lines are NOT eligible for mega class exception and MUST be refactored.
    </note>
    <note>
      This exception list must be reviewed and approved by Principal Engineer role.
    </note>
    <note>
      New exceptions require explicit BVJ (Business Value Justification).
    </note>
    <note>
      Mega classes must have dedicated integration tests validating SSOT behavior.
    </note>
  </compliance_notes>

  <planned_improvements>
    <improvement type="naming_clarity">
      <description>Business-focused naming to replace confusing "Manager" terminology</description>
      <reference>reports/architecture/MANAGER_RENAMING_PLAN_20250908.md</reference>
      <planned_renames>
        <rename>
          <current>UnifiedConfigurationManager</current>
          <proposed>PlatformConfiguration</proposed>
          <rationale>Name directly reflects business function - this IS the platform's configuration system</rationale>
        </rename>
        <rename>
          <current>UnifiedStateManager</current>
          <proposed>ApplicationState</proposed>
          <rationale>Name directly reflects business function - this IS the application's state store</rationale>
        </rename>
        <rename>
          <current>UnifiedLifecycleManager</current>
          <proposed>SystemLifecycle</proposed>
          <rationale>Name directly reflects business function - this IS the system's lifecycle controller</rationale>
        </rename>
        <rename>
          <current>UnifiedWebSocketManager</current>
          <proposed>RealtimeCommunications</proposed>
          <rationale>Emphasizes business value (real-time communications) over implementation (WebSocket)</rationale>
        </rename>
        <rename>
          <current>DatabaseManager</current>
          <proposed>DataAccess</proposed>
          <rationale>Emphasizes what it provides (data access) rather than administrative function</rationale>
        </rename>
      </planned_renames>
      <implementation_status>Planned for Q4 2025</implementation_status>
    </improvement>
  </planned_improvements>
</mega_class_exceptions>