<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<specification>
    <metadata>
        <name>Self Checks</name>
        <type>selfchecks</type>
        <version>1.0</version>
    </metadata>
    
    <checks>
        <check id="1">
            <title>Configuration Validation</title>
            <what>Implement a check to validate the application's configuration (app/config.py) on startup</what>
            <why>This would ensure that all required settings are present and have valid values (e.g., checking if URLs are well-formed, or that required API keys are not empty). This can prevent runtime errors caused by misconfiguration</why>
        </check>
        
        <check id="2">
            <title>External Service Connectivity</title>
            <what>Add checks to verify the connectivity to all external services the application depends on</what>
            <why>Your application uses Redis, ClickHouse, and an external LLM provider. A startup check could attempt to connect to each of these services and report an error if any of them are unavailable. This would provide a clear and immediate signal that a dependency is down, rather than discovering it through a failed user request</why>
        </check>
        
        <check id="3">
            <title>API Key Validation</title>
            <what>For services that require API keys (like the LLM provider), you could add a check to make a simple, inexpensive API call to validate that the keys are correct and have the necessary permissions</what>
            <why>This would catch issues with invalid or expired API keys at startup, which is much better than failing in the middle of a user's workflow</why>
        </check>
        
        <check id="4">
            <title>File System Permissions</title>
            <what>If your application needs to write to specific directories (e.g., for logs, file uploads, or temporary files), you could add a check to verify that these directories exist and that the application has the necessary write permissions</what>
            <why>This would prevent runtime errors when the application tries to write a file to a location that doesn't exist or isn't writable</why>
        </check>
        
        <check id="5">
            <title>Tool and Agent Integrity Check</title>
            <what>You could implement a check to verify the integrity of your agent's tools. This could involve checking if the tool's dependencies are met and if the tool's configuration is valid</what>
            <why>As you add more tools to your agents, this check would ensure that a misconfigured or broken tool doesn't bring down the entire agent system</why>
        </check>
    </checks>
</specification>